Fabio Battaglia

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Born in Italy, 22-Sep-1990 6 Cromwell Mansions, King Street, London, UK W69JX

□ (+44) 750 383 1291 · (+39) 340 381 35 42 | Safabio.battaglia90@gmail.com | 🖸 farbiondriven | 📓 farbiondriven | 🗖 fabiobattaglia90

Summary_

Software Engineer with experience on high availability systems for Biometric Security and Travel Industry. I currently work as a Lead Software Engineer for Remark AI, a biometric system application provider, in London. I'm result oriented, I have good interpersonal and organizational skills, I'm proactive and capable of working effectively with no supervision. I regularly contribute over the stack exchange community and on Github.

Work Experience

Court of Justice of the European Union

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Sep. 2020 - present

- Trainee at the Chamber of the Italian Advocate General G. Pitruzzella
- Drafting the AG's Legal Opinions.
- Providing advice on both substantive and procedural points of law arising from cases.
- Conducting legal research on the AG's cases.

BonelliErede Law Firm Brussels, Belgium

LEGAL ADVISOR, EU LAW DEPARTMENT

Mar. 2019 - Sep 2020

- In charge of relevant cases brought before the EU Courts against the European Parlament, about pension rights of former european deputies.
- Working on cases concerning mergers and acquisitions, joint ventures, cartels state aid and other fields of Competition Law, including participation in proceedings before the Italian Antitrust Authorities, the European Commission and the Court of justice.
- Assisting with the implementation of a merger between two market leaders in the oil and gas sector.
- Advising the most leading telecommunication enterprises on State Aid in ultra broadband infrastructure domains.
- · Advising a market leader in the transport sector in relation to the interpretation of the new EU Regulation about CO2 emissions.

European Commission Brussels, Belgium

BLUEBOOK TRAINEESHIP, LEGAL SERVICE, EUROPEAN CIVIL SERVICE LAW UNIT

Oct. 2018 - Feb. 2019

- Assisting the Commission Legal Service lawyers in providing legal support to the Commission services for the European Commission staff matters.
- Consultations concerning the legal assessments and review of drafts made by DG HR, on the matter of recruitment, disciplinary measures, career managements, pension rights and the interpretation of the Staff Regulation in general.
- Litigations: drafting a long submission before the General Court in action for annulment against EU Commission's decision on a case of Harassment, preparation of the hearing before the General Court in a prominent case.

Avvocatura Generale dello Stato

Rome, Italy

Nov. 2016 - Nov. 2017

• Working with Italian central administrations and Authorities in the fields of EU Law and Administrative Law.

- Assisting in judicial proceedings and providing legal advice to Constitutional Bodies and Public Administration.
- Providing advice on the quality of draft proposals for legal acts (public procurement domain).

Roma Tre University and LUMSA University

Rome, Italy

ACADEMIC ASSISTANT

TRAINEE LAWYER

Oct. 2013 - Nov. 2017

- · Assisting the Professor during exams and lessons.
- Conducting legal research on national and EU legislation
- Participation in research projects such as: The Law of State Aid in the European Union, Possible European Union (Unione Europea Possibile), EU energy policy integration.
- Tutoring activities to support students.
- Organizing a relevant conference concerning the recent development on judicial control on the acts of Independents Administrative Authorities.

Cabinet d'avocat International De Arcangelis

Paris, France

LEGAL TRAINEE

Mar. 2011 - Jul. 2011

- · Writing legal documents.
- Legal translation (from French to Italian and vice versa).
- · Drafting a complaint before the EU Commission about the infringement by the Italian State of EU Law.

Education

College of Europe Bruges, Belgium

ADVANCED MASTER ON EUROPEAN UNION LAW (LL.M)

Sept. 2017 - June. 2018

- Beneficiary of the excellence-based ENP Scholarship
- Thesis: "Human rights clauses in the EU'S International agreements, with focus on the Association Agreements in the Eastern neighbourhood". Supervisor: M. Maresceau
- Attending intensive course "EU State Aid Law", held by Prof. M. Merola

Università degli Studi Roma Tre

Rome, Italy

FULL DEGREE IN LAW (JD EQUIVALENT)

Oct. 2009 - Sept. 2016

• Final Mark: 110/110 cum laude with special mention

Université Paris 1 Panthéon-Sorbonne

Paris, France

RESEARCH THESIS ABROAD

May 2016 - July 2016

- Thesis: Le contrôl juridictionnel sur les décisions de sanction des autorités administratives indépendantes: vers un modèle commun européen
- Supervisors: Prof. G. Rossi, Prof. E. Cardi, Prof. D. Capitant

Université Paris Descartes Paris, France

EXCHANGE PROGRAM

Oct. 2011 - June 2012

• Eight exams passed with distinctioned related to EU law, International Law, Civil Law

University of Malta Msida, Malta

Exchange Program Sept. 2014 - Jan. 2015

· Four exams passed with distinctioned related to EU law, Competiton Law, Commercial Law

Skills

Languages Italian: mother tongue. French: full professional proficiency. English: full professional proficiency

IT Skills Proficient in Microsoft Office Applications, GenDoc, Sysper

Legal Applications EurLex, LexisLibrary, DeJure, Lex24

Publications

- Research project organized by Roma Tre University (Prof. G. Rossi, Mario P. Chiti, G. Corso, Dian Schefold) in collaboration with the Italian Senate: "L'Unione Europea possibile e necessaria: l'Europa a cerchi concentrici"
- The determination of the object of the availment contract (avvalimento) in the public tender.

References_

Giovanni Pitruzzella Advocate General - Court of Justice of the European Union

Massimo Merola Managing Partner - BonelliErede Law Firm, Brussels office; Professor - College of Europe in Bruges, Belgium

Bernard Mongin Legal Advisor - European Commission's Legal Service; Ancien référendaire - Court of Justice of the European Union